Leah: When a child or young
person shows signs of experiencing
mental health concerns, usually
the first line treatments include
psychological therapies or medication.
However, there are other approaches
that can help such as changing lifestyle
factors that influence mental health.
Simple positive lifestyle changes that
can be made by Improving diet, increasing
exercise, prioritising sleep and rest,
and reaching out for help when needed.
Rhiannon: Children and young people can
be encouraged to improve their fitness
by just getting out more walking or
playing as short bouts of activity can
provide an immediate elevation of mood.
Encouraging children and young
people to limit exposure to mobile
phones, computer and TV use or any
other substance if its excessive.
Helping them to regulate their actions
can have positive benefits for sleep and
mood, and therefore their mental health.
Leah: Spending time with nature such as
having a pet has many positive effects
and may also boost feelings of well-being.
Exposure to sunshine helps
produce serotonin and boosts
vitamin D levels, which also has a
positive effect on mental health.
Positive lifestyle changes aren't
a replacement for medication or
psychological therapy but something
people can undertake themselves,
on top of their treatment.
Rhiannon: Social support is often
identified as an important component
of good relationships and strong
psychological health and involves having
a network of family and friends that
can be turned to in times of need.
Social support involves advice,
care, empathy and concern
anytime or when most needed.
Others can help take care of physical
needs especially when people have
immediate needs that must be addressed
for example when a child has worries
about their workload for school.
Some can provide informational support
providing guidance, advice, information,
and mentoring especially important when
making decisions or big life changes.
Leah: Being surrounded by people who
are caring and supportive helps children
and young people to deal more readily
with the stresses that life brings.